Tim and his cofounders launched the company with two million dollars in funding. They were out of cash the next year. Now, lots of companies fold at that point, but Tim chose to fight. He maxed out 11 credit cards and racked up six figures in personal debt and it still wasn't enough. So every two weeks for two years on payday he stood in front of his employees and he asked them to sacrifice their salaries, and it worked. More than 50 people deferred two million dollars, and now, more than a decade later, Pandora is worth billions. When you believe that there is a way around or through whatever is in front of you, that surrender is not an option, you can overcome enormous obstacles. Which brings us to soap opera lesson two: sacrifice your ego and drop the superiority complex. Now, this is scary. It's an acknowledgment of need or fallibility. Maybe it's even an admission that we're not as special as we might like to think. Stephanie Forrester of "The Bold and the Beautiful" thought she was pretty darn special. She thought she was so special, she didn't need to mix with the riffraff from the valley, and she made sure valley girl Brooke knew it. But after nearly 25 years of epic fighting, Stephanie got sick and let Brooke in. They made amends, archenemies became soul mates and Stephanie died in Brooke's arms, and here's our takeaway. Drop your ego.
Tim y sus cofundadores lanzaron una empresa con USD 2 millones de capital. Un año después, ya no tenían fondos. Muchas empresas fracasan en ese punto, pero Tim eligió pelear. Agotó 11 tarjetas de crédito y acumuló seis cifras en deudas personales y aún no fue suficiente. Durante dos años, cada día de pago se plantó frente a sus empleados y les pidió que sacrificaran sus salarios, y funcionó. Más de 50 personas concedieron USD 2 millones, y ahora, más de una década después, Pandora vale mil millones. Cuando crees que hay una forma de sortear lo que tienes ante ti, que rendirse no es una opción, puedes superar obstáculos enormes. Lo que nos lleva a la lección número 2: Sacrifica tu ego y deja el complejo de superioridad. Esto da miedo. Es el reconocimiento de necesidad o falibilidad. Tal vez es incluso admitir que no somos tan especiales como nos gustaría pensar. Stephanie Forrester de "The Bold and the Beautiful" pensaba que era bastante especial. Pensaba que era tan especial, que no necesitaba mezclarse con la chusma del valle y se aseguró de que Brooke lo supiera. Pero tras casi 25 años de batalla épica, Stephanie se enfermó y dejó entrar a Brooke. Hicieron las paces, las archienemigas se hicieron almas gemelas y Stephanie murió en brazos de Brooke, y aquí está el mensaje. Deja el ego.
Life is not about you. It's about us, and our ability to experience joy and love and to improve our reality comes only when we make ourselves vulnerable and we accept responsibility for our actions and our inactions, kind of like Howard Schultz, the CEO of Starbucks. Now, after a great run as CEO, Howard stepped down in 2000, and Starbucks quickly overextended itself and stock prices fell. Howard rejoined the team in 2008, and one of the first things he did was apologize to all 180,000 employees. He apologized. And then he asked for help, honesty, and ideas in return. And now, Starbucks has more than doubled its net revenue since Howard came back. So sacrifice your desire to be right or safe all the time. It's not helping anyone, least of all you. Sacrifice your ego. Soap opera lesson three: evolution is real. You're not meant to be static characters. On television, static equals boring and boring equals fired. Characters are supposed to grow and change. Now, on TV, those dynamic changes can make for some rough transitions, particularly when a character is played by one person yesterday and played by someone new today. Recasting happens all the time on soaps. Over the last 20 years, four different actors have played the same key role of Carly Benson on "General Hospital." Each new face triggered a change in the character's life and personality. Now, there was always an essential nugget of Carly in there, but the character and the story adapted to whomever was playing her. And here's what that means for us. While we may not swap faces in our own lives, we can evolve too. We can choose to draw a circle around our feet and stay in that spot, or we can open ourselves to opportunities like Carly, who went from nursing student to hotel owner, or like Julia Child. Julia was a World War II spy, and when the war ended, she got married, moved to France, and decided to give culinary school a shot. Julia, her books and her TV shows revolutionized the way America cooks. We all have the power to initiate change in our lives, to evolve and adapt. We make the choice, but sometimes life chooses for us, and we don't get a heads up.
La vida no se trata de ti. Es sobre nosotros y nuestra habilidad para experimentar felicidad y amor, y mejorar nuestra realidad llega sólo al ser también vulnerables y aceptamos la responsabilidad por nuestras acciones y nuestras no acciones, como Howard Schultz, el CEO de Starbucks. Luego de una gran carrera como CEO, Howard dejó el cargo en 2000, y Starbucks se desencarriló rápidamente y las acciones cayeron. Howard se reincorporó al equipo en 2008, y una de las primeras cosas que hizo fue disculparse ante los 180 000 empleados. Se disculpó. Y luego, a cambio, pidió ayuda, honestidad e ideas. Y Starbucks ha más que duplicado sus ingresos netos desde que Howard volvió. Así que sacrifica tu deseo de estar acertado o seguro todo el tiempo. No ayuda a nadie, y menos a ti. Sacrifica tu ego. Lección número 3 de telenovela: La evolución es real. No se supone que seas un personaje estático. En televisión, estático es aburrido, y aburrido es despedido. Se supone que los personajes crecen y cambian. Bien, en TV, esos cambios dinámicos pueden llevar a transiciones duras, en particular cuando ayer un personaje lo interpretaba una persona y hoy lo interpreta otra. Los cambios de reparto suceden todo el tiempo en las telenovelas. En los últimos 20 años, cuatro actrices interpretaron el mismo papel protagónico de Carly Benson en "General Hospital". Cada rostro nuevo generaba un cambio en la vida y personalidad del personaje. Siempre hubo un pedacito esencial de Carly allí, pero el personaje y la historia se adaptaron a quien la interpretaba. Y esto es lo que significa para nosotros. Aunque no podemos cambiar de rostro en nuestras vidas, nosotros también podemos evolucionar. Podemos elegir pintarnos un círculo alrededor de los pies y quedarnos allí, o podemos abrirnos a las oportunidades, como Carly, quien pasó de estudiante de enfermería a dueña de hotel, o como Julia Child. Julia era una espía en la Segunda Guerra Mundial, y cuando terminó la guerra, se casó y se mudó a Francia, y decidió probar con la escuela de cocina. Julia, sus libros y programas de TV revolucionaron la cocina estadounidense. Todos tenemos el poder de comenzar el cambio en nuestras vidas, de evolucionar y adaptarnos. Nosotros elegimos, pero a veces la vida lo elige por nosotros y nadie nos avisa previamente.
Surprise slams us in the face. You're flat on the ground, the air is gone, and you need resuscitation. So thank goodness for soap opera lesson four: resurrection is possible. (Laughter) (Applause) In 1983, "Days of Our Lives"' Stefano DiMera died of a stroke, but not really, because in 1984 he died when his car plunged into the harbor, and yet he was back in 1985 with a brain tumor. (Laughter) But before the tumor could kill him, Marlena shot him, and he tumbled off a catwalk to his death. And so it went for 30 years. (Laughter) Even when we saw the body, we knew better. He's called the Phoenix for a reason. And here's what that means for us.
La sorpresa nos golpea en el rostro. Quedas en el piso sin aire y necesitas que te resuciten. Gracias a Dios tenemos la lección número 4 de telenovela: La resurrección es posible. (Risas) (Aplausos) En 1983, Stefano DiMera de "Days of Our Lives" murió de un ataque cardíaco, pero en realidad no, porque en 1984 murió cuando se le averió el auto en el puerto, y volvió en 1985 con un tumor cerebral. (Risas) Pero antes de que el tumor lo matara, Marlena le disparó, y murió al caerse de una pasarela. Y así sucedió por 30 años. (Risas) Aún cuando vimos el cuerpo, sabíamos la verdad. Por algo lo llaman el Fénix. Y ésto es lo que significa para nosotros.
As long as the show is still on the air, or you're still breathing, nothing is permanent. Resurrection is possible. Now, of course, just like life, soap operas do ultimately meet the big finale. CBS canceled my show, "As The World Turns," in December 2009, and we shot our final episode in June 2010. It was six months of dying and I rode that train right into the mountain. And even though we were in the middle of a huge recession
Siempre que el show este al aire, o tú todavía respires, nada es permanente. La resurrección es posible. Por supuesto, como en la vida, las telenovelas en algún momento llegan al gran final. CBS canceló mi show, "As The World Turns" en diciembre de 2009, y filmamos el último episodio en junio de 2010. Fueron seis meses de muerte y seguí en el tren hasta chocar la montaña. Y aunque estábamos en medio de una enorme recesión
and millions of people were struggling to find work, I somehow thought everything would be OK. So I packed up the kids and the Brooklyn apartment, and we moved in with my in-laws in Alabama. (Laughter) Three months later, nothing was OK. That was when I watched the final episode air, and I realized the show was not the only fatality. I was one too. I was unemployed and living on the second floor of my in-laws' home, and that's enough to make anyone feel dead inside. (Laughter) But I knew my story wasn't over, that it couldn't be over. I just had to tap into everything I had ever learned about soap operas. I had to be brave like Erica and refuse to surrender, so every day, I made a decision to fight.
y millones de personas luchaban por conseguir trabajo, pensé que de algún modo todo estaría bien. Así que empaqué a mis hijos y el departamento en Brooklyn y me mudé con mis suegros a Alabama. (Risas) Tres meses después, nada estaba bien. Fue cuando vi la emisión del último episodio y me di cuenta de que el show no era la única fatalidad. Yo también lo era. Era desempleada y vivía en el segundo piso de la casa de mis suegros, y eso es suficiente para sentirse muerta por dentro. (Risas) Pero sabía que mi historia no había terminado, que no podía terminar. Sólo tenía que aprovechar todo lo que había aprendido de las novelas. Tenía que ser valiente como Érica y no rendirme, así que todos los días, decidí pelear.
I had to be vulnerable like Stephanie and sacrifice my ego. I had to ask for help a lot of times across many states. I had to be adaptable like Carly and evolve my skills, my mindset, and my circumstances, and then I had to be resilient, like Stefano, and resurrect myself and my career like a phoenix from the ashes. Eventually I got an interview. After 15 years in news and entertainment, nine months of unemployment and this one interview, I had an offer for an entry level job. I was 37 years old and I was back from the dead. We will all experience what looks like an ending, and we can choose to make it a beginning. Kind of like Tina, who miraculously survived that waterfall, and because I hate to leave a cliffhanger hanging, Tina and Cord did get divorced, but they got remarried three times before the show went off the air in 2012. So remember, as long as there is breath in your body, it's never too late to change your story. Thank you. (Applause)
Tenía que ser vulnerable como Stephanie y sacrificar mi ego. Tuve que pedir ayuda muchas veces en muchos estados. Tenía que ser adaptable como Carly y desarrollar mis habilidades, mi actitud y mis circunstancias, y luego tenía que ser perseverante, como Stefano, y resucitarme a mí y a mi carrera como el ave fénix de sus cenizas. Al final tuve una entrevista. Tras 15 años en noticias y entretenimiento, nueve meses de desempleo y esta entrevista, me ofrecieron un trabajo de principiante. Tenía 37 años y había vuelto de la muerte. Todos experimentaremos algo que parece un final, y podemos elegir convertirlo en un comienzo. Como Tina, que milagrosamente sobrevivió la cascada y como odio los finales en suspenso, Tina y Cord sí se divorciaron, pero volvieron a casarse tres veces antes de que cancelaran el show en 2012. Así que recuerden, mientras todavía respiren, nunca es tarde para cambiar su historia. Gracias. (Aplausos)